[Music]
hi everybody
i recently sat down with tyson juncker
porter who's just released a new book
called sam talk how indigenous thinking
can save the world
and it's made quite a big splash tyson's
from the appellate clan
in northern queensland in australia and
he's also a senior lecturer
in indigenous knowledges at deakin
university in melbourne
so what's special about the book is that
tyson is taking an indigenous
perspective and using that to look back
at western culture
and he's really looking at a lot of the
topics like
systems change and complexity that we've
been exploring in rebel wisdom
anybody who thinks they've got a
solution or they have a plan or a design
or anything like that um they're an
idiot
you can't dynamic systems don't operate
like that
you know you have a thing called
emergence we know this we know the
science on it
and you know emergence is the only thing
that can deal with
these kind of complexities so all you
can do is foster the conditions for
emergence
tyson also brings a really unique
perspective on a lot of the cultural
dynamics that we've explored on the
channel so
everything from the culture wars through
to economics
in any theory if you're just focusing on
a few little snippets
that fit with your personal brand and
you're barking those things that
everyone else
like an idiot then
then you're gonna be an idiot and um
i i really can't see
where it's coming from this idea that um
that that is just a trait of the left
or the social justice warriors or anyone
because i'm seeing
everybody doing that i'm seeing people
who are claiming centrism especially
doing that
but everybody's critiquing everybody
else in very shallow ways
and he also doesn't hold his punches
when he's talking about where
our current systems and trajectory in
the west is leading us
you know where you used to have family
and community now you're gonna have
um you're gonna have the economy
and government the economy in the state
and um
and we're going to provide all the
things for you that land used to provide
um but you have to sell us a third of
your life
the trade-off is you have to give us a
third of your life
like you're gonna have to spend the
other third another third sleeping
oh and by the way a sizable chunk of the
third that's left over you're gonna have
to spend commuting
life maintenance tasks paying your bills
make sure you
account it um oh and and you're not
going to be getting any exercise anymore
bro so you need to set aside an hour for
that
yeah that's all right we're going to
provide you with these little shitty
indoor spaces
where you can lift heavy things that
don't need lifting
and pedal on a bike that goes nowhere
and run even though nothing's chasing
you and you're not chasing anything
and you're not in a hurry you're gonna
do all those pointless tasks
and you're going to do them over and
over and over
until you fucking die and that's
progress
oh god so tyson yunkaporta thanks a lot
for being here
yeah it's good to be here yeah so tyson
uh
your book sand talk is is creating quite
a splash at the moment um and
generating a lot of interest be really
great to hear just a little bit about
like
what's what's the key message or some of
the key messages in the book
um yeah it's basically a reversal
uh usually when people look at
indigenous knowledge it's um
it's it's examining you know the content
of indigenous knowledge you know and
uh snippets of it um from
from a non-indigenous perspective or
it's always
even if it's an indigenous voice it's
about trying to explain
our knowledge uh to the rest of the
world
although santorum doesn't do that it
kind of flips things around
so um santok is
looking at the world from an indigenous
perspective
so it's um taking that indigenous
knowledge standpoint
and using that as a lens to have a look
at what's going on in the world
yeah so it's kind of turning it back
it's like reverse anthropology
really and it's a really cheeky book
it's not done in like an aggressive way
or a blamey way or like going ah
you're like this privilege that
privilege whatever it's
it's kind of just fun you know we kind
of do some thought experiments have a
few laughs tell some yarns
and then there's a few slaps in there
just for fun
too but um yeah people enjoy it
it seems and it looks like i mean it
really strongly invites the reader to
bring
their stories alongside and their
knowledge alongside and amongst
uh all of that knowledge and so in that
way you know it's designed to be
a book that no two people would read the
same book everybody's reading a
different book when they come there
because they're bringing their
standpoint
to that and finding a safe space to um
just experiment with that experiment
with these
these different viewpoints world views
life worlds coming together
um yeah so it's a bit of fun
nice and what what made you decide to
write it i know you have uh
you know a really really interesting
background which you might go into in a
bit but like
why now like why this why now uh
um i i just i needed the money and they
offered me a
five thousand dollar advance
that's why and it was work i was doing
anyway but i was just doing it verbally
you know i had
messages that have been uh
you know i've been given these
tasks to do by elders where they you
need to pass on this message
out to as many people as you can you
need to get these symbols
particularly from old man juma in the
book uh but several other elders as well
and lots of other people
they um you know so i just basically
been going around and
and uh yarning with people for 20 years
getting those messages out there
and um i couldn't think of anything else
to write about so i just i wrote about
that
and i thought it would be a labor-saving
device like it would save me from having
too many more yarns because they're
exhausting but not
it's just exponentially increased the
amount of conversations
that i have to have and um
you know and straining all of my
relationships and doing so i'm
i'm on borrowed time i'm using up all my
related relational credit here
in this house
well yeah i'm glad you're making it
there's people out there like vacuuming
and
trying to feed people and bathe people
right now not happy with me not being
there doing that
you know are you off having your yards
are you that's great
who's gonna watch this fridge
yeah brilliant so
yeah i mean on the subject of yarns you
just described really nicely that the
the way in which
sand talk and i suppose the the world
view you're exploring
is based on many different stories
coming together you know everywhere yeah
and of course like the land has stories
as well and is speaking and teaching us
so there's all this kind of
interconnection of stories and yarns the
telling of stories there's a huge part
of sound talk
now in a way it's it's a kind of very
you know you could see it as a very
post-modern
thing this kind of coming weaving
together of many different perspectives
and we've we've spoken a little bit
before and i was really interested in
your take on
on post modernism you have a kind of
unique perspective because you
you have this perspective of
understanding that these kind of
multiple
viewpoints exist but you're also you
know you're also holding quite i think a
nuanced position
and we've talked a lot on the channel
and looked a lot from the very beginning
of rebel wisdom
on like looking at the culture wars and
looking at this kind of
tension between you know one side of the
culture
there's the entities like the idw and
the others which is you know described
as kind of woke or social justice
and this big tension between them that's
happening i think you know
when we've talked you have interesting
synthesis around these things so i
thought it'd be interesting to talk a
little bit about
maybe beginning with where you think
postmodernism has gone too far and then
going into where you think it's really
offered a valuable perspective but maybe
we could start where
where you think it it has gone too far
in the culture and where it's not
helpful
yeah but the language of going too far
is like
i don't know it always makes me feel
like god daddy will smack
you know and i do hear that phrase a lot
and and and and it's often not with you
but um
it's often followed by just a remarkable
process of um
of you know uh critiquing
like critiquing critical theory
uh post-modernism uh post-structuralism
deconstructivism all these things it
sort of delivers a bit of a
blistering critique of those things
using the tools
of critique that are just
so i see like um yeah all these
downtrodden powerful
cultural groups sort of rising up to
use the victims tools to
deconstruct the victim's house or so i i
don't quite get it
look so you've got um you know critical
theory critical race theory
you know all of these things are
theories and what is a theory
well a theory is wrong for a start
like that's the limit and any scientist
will tell you the same
every theory is wrong but it can be
useful in certain contexts
you know newton's physics it helps
it's helping with the vacuuming that's
happening out there right now
i think you can probably hear that
vacuum cleaner you know newton's physics
works in certain contexts
but in order for this zoom meeting to
take place we probably don't want to go
with newton we
probably want to go with einstein
otherwise
the signal won't work because you know
time changes for this when the signal
bounces up to the satellite
the further you go from the earth time
changes so you're going to need einstein
for a bit
but then he's only good up to a point
you need to switch between theories
and i guess if you're living in
complexity and dealing with complex
problems
in a complex world then you need to
borrow from lots of
theories simultaneously
so i mean basically you know if you read
my book um and a lot of very
conservative people who read my book and
really loved it
and i don't think they realize that what
i'm doing there is
is standpoint theory and and it's
grounded in a lot of deconstructivism
simply because these are the things that
have allowed me the tools to
to come into the space you know um i
have problems with post-modernism but
it's mostly
from an indigenous perspective
post-modernism is placeless
you know it's ethereal it's floating in
space it doesn't
you know all indigenous knowledge is
grounded strongly in place
and it's very spatial you know it always
is so
postmodernism is not a good tool for
that however post-modernism
deconstructivism and particularly
post-colonialism
has been a very good tool for us to be
able to enter the academy
and to assert our standpoint and to to
make sure that we're able to think
and inquire from our standpoint
which is a very difficult thing to
explain but
and this has given rise to lots of
really good things i don't know if
you've ever heard of misty jenkins
uh but misty jenkins is an aboriginal
woman from australia
um from uganda tomorrow mob
and she's like she's one of the top
genetic researchers on the planet
uh at the moment she's got a lab where
she's she's pretty much sorting out
brain cancer
but um she but she's come up with one of
the one of the very big
discoveries that completely
revolutionized genetic science
and it was her you know grounding in her
indigenous standpoint
making room for her to be able to apply
um
our patterns of logic to what she was
studying
and to bring in other variables that are
usually out there like
time and place and season and things
like that
um to be able to bring those things in
that's what's allowed her to make those
discoveries
so you can't throw the baby out with the
bath water
you know um most of the post-colonial
and decolonizing
methodologies we have in the indigenous
academy
you know we we have to acknowledge uh
post-structural feminism uh for their
legacy
you know um you don't have to be a
post-structuralist feminist
to use those tools you know we pick
those things up and there's a lot of
problematic stuff in there
you know and a lot of um you know women
of color around the world
uh you know have you know done the hard
work of actually
critiquing the stuff that's that's in
there and trying to find more creative
ways to do the work
um but i guess in any theory if you're
just focusing on a few little snippets
that fit with your personal brand and
you're barking those things that
everyone else
like an idiot then
then you're gonna be an idiot and um
i i really can't see
where it's coming from this idea that um
that that is just a trait of the left or
the
social justice warriors or anyone
because i'm seeing everybody doing that
i'm seeing people who are claiming
centrism especially doing that
but everybody's critiquing everybody
else in very shallow ways
and when they're looking at the bell
curve
it's great to include the outliers in
your analysis
because they're part of the story too
but if you just focus on the outliers
the tales of the distribution
then your analysis is not going to be
accurate
so if you're only looking at youtube
videos of sjws
when they're angry and you're going oh
that's what post-modernism is
then it's not going to work it's it's
not going to be valid
where's the validity where's the rigor
that you are claiming
because all these people are always
claiming this i'm being objective and
empirical
the data doesn't lie so i'm going to
quote one statistic
out of context and make it look like all
males of color are rapists
and well you can't argue with the
statistics i'm just being rational
it's like they're in a context bros and
your analysis is rubbish
it's absolute rubbish it's not
empirical you're not the positivist
voice of reason and empiricism and truth
you're just an idiot who can't see his
own standpoint
and you have one you have a standpoint
that is shaping the knowledge you're
presenting and the analysis you're doing
it's just that you can't see it it's
invisible to you
so you know um
as i said before it's um fuco ain't woke
you can't brand the entire the entire
body of knowledge
it's developed over decades you can't
brand that
under that one sjw that you saw on
youtube
because fuco's got his act together and
the libertarian
right
deploys his critique of neo-liberalism
you know
very well they never cite him though
you don't see them saying oh yeah this
is from bordeaux
but um you know that that that came
after 911 you know with the freedom
fries
there was an enormous backlash in the
culture wars against anything french
and unfortunately deconstructivism
critique post-modernism all these things
came under fire
and i don't know if you saw this in the
states but in australia
it was just a newspaper campaign
that basically up ended the entire
curriculum
school curriculum in australia removed
anything that's smacked of that evil
french post-modernism
because it's freedom fries and you're
going back to the
reading writing and arithmetic you know
because that's empirical and that's that
that's common sense you know
that's awesome i mean i find foucault
really
still very useful and in particular
looking at how
institutions uh exercise power
and that that's a critique everyone's
you know most people are using that
critique as
you say um yeah you you know you go into
that you go into
the the way in which our let's say our
institutions but maybe more broadly our
entire systems
are effectively taking us towards a a
kind of
a zero-sum point um you know in san talk
be interesting to hear a little bit
about what
what does that indigenous perspective um
show us that we might not see from from
within our our current systems and
whatever you want to call it western
capitalism or maybe it's probably better
terms for it
um i i think it's i mean the most
important gift is just
reclaiming the adaptive capacity of our
species
you know it is our unique gift
you know as the custodial species of
this planet it's our unique gift to be
able to adapt
to massive changes and massive traumas
and acceptance is just uh you know it's
part of our human knowledge systems
any knowledge system that is still human
and not domesticated
acceptance is is part of that kind of in
the tradition of the greek stoics and
all that kind of thing
you know um yeah i think that that's
that's some of the unique gifts that um
that that knowledge can bring out
but all that knowledge is really just
human knowledge
you know the knowledge of undomesticated
humans how we actually
are our nature so i mean so inherently
uh
human beings are opposed to the genetic
level
um to any kind of hierarchies permanent
hierarchies
um and and permanent power imbalances
monopolies things like this
you know for i mean well over a million
years we've been living in societies
that are
you know that do not respond to that
very well
you know and most of our societies
are set up um to prevent that from
happening
i said there's this last ten thousand
year blip of a bit of an experiment
and particularly the last few centuries
where um you know that's taken over a
bit but that won't last much longer
in the book you talk about the the way
in which aboriginal culture is sort of
geared up to make sure that narcissism
doesn't take over
and that that is it's a huge part of it
you know we were just talking about
the culture wars and this this sense of
everyone thinking that they're right and
everyone you know doubling down on
reason or doubling down on
on deconstruction or whatever it might
be it strikes me that
there's this rampant narcissism in our
culture and it goes much deeper than
just
a particular spat on twitter it goes
right down to the core of it so
so what what aboriginal culture you know
in what ways can it help us get get a
new lens on that on our own narcissism
let's say
um i i think it's about just getting
back to natural law
uh you know like like i was saying there
is that
inherent sort of abhorrence of the idea
of anybody
you know getting one over anyone else or
dominating
you know the idea of one story
or one point of view coming out on top
and being the one story to rule them all
is absolute anathema to us all at the
molecular level
we cannot accept that you know as human
beings
um we all hate that but we're kind of
trapped in it at the moment
you know and it's just there's such
weird fractal things going on so even
you've mentioned before you know
doubling down
um that's a critique an attempted
critique
to try and expose the pattern of
communication that's going on at the
moment
but as soon as we put that out there
um everybody picked it up and that just
became another layer
to the purity testing going on you know
so everybody's accusing everybody else
of doubling down
whenever they say anything um you know
it's um yeah it's
it's it's it's just fractal
um misery what's going on
misery stacked misery stacked misery in
in all communication at the moment
and it's it's lawless behavior
because all we have is paper law digital
law
um whatever that is that is ephemeral
uh coming from institutions that we
don't trust anymore
um so i think it's you see every time
there's a disaster people fall back on
natural law
like we always see where there's a
disaster a disaster basically
you could define it as any situation
that
knocks the control of the state and the
the mechanisms of the state out of
operation for a while
that's what a disaster is and into that
gap
floods all this natural law um
from the human beings and and the
landscape that they inhabit
um suddenly we just get back into it and
you always hear about it after the
disasters
there's always feel good news reports
about you know how everybody came
together cooperatively
and collaborated and lifted themselves
out and you
see people interviewed and they're not
um
miserable or scared or upset about the
disaster
they're kind of really excited on a bit
of a high
about the you know the marketplace that
emerged
uh the sharing economy that emerged in
which everybody was
supporting each other and everybody
suddenly found that they were all quite
prosperous
and all had everything that they needed
just through that through that
free-flowing exchange with no monopolies
and no controls
then the state comes back in and get and
gets control you see it in like you know
um you know when there's a coup or
something
you see it in sudan and places like that
somalia
all around the world you see these
temporary uh disruptions
uh to all these institutions that we
just don't trust anymore
um you see that emergence of natural law
and so that's that's that's just that's
what people need to get back to
but if if anybody gives i hesitate even
to call it natural law because that's a
label
and then people will be purity testing
on that just whatever you do don't give
it a name
all you can do is foster the conditions
for emergence
and allow it to emerge and just behave
with integrity
and you know maybe others will do the
same
but the minute you have an idea and you
think this is an important idea
everybody should know about this
everybody should be doing this
as soon as you do that that's you've
made an ideology and you're stuffed
you've made a closed system and entropy
is the only thing that can ensue
yeah so i'm curious about how this
applies or how this could apply because
i suppose a
uh a critic might say yeah but we've got
all these supply chains like how are we
going to
without those how are we going to feed
everyone all of that
so so what are what are some of the ways
that we might
rethink it rather than just going no but
we need the state we need those laws etc
like
yeah for some people we're already we're
already starting to go
how are we going to feed everybody for
the next decade
the supply chains have been so
catastrophically disrupted
and they're so complicated that nobody
understands how they work
so we can't just tinker them back
together again
what's going to happen so we're already
there you know
how will we make it work well you know i
guess your
your um your
freed slaves uh in in the united states
uh had that same conundrum so remember
they were promised 40 acres in a mule
you remember that where did that go
forget about reparations just give
everybody the equivalent of 40 acres and
a mule
that that'd be good how much does that
cost now that's worth a bit
you start that off but they didn't get
the 40 acres in a mule they were just
dumped and so they had to like just with
the clothes on their back
and the work of their hands they had to
try and build communities
now the economic systems that they
created in their
communities they were a very different
economic system
you know they were collaborative
collective
and um you know these these
these really dynamic sharing economies
where
every unit of value every hard one unit
of value
had a lot of velocity within that system
so although there wasn't very much
wealth there there was
amazing prosperity so you ended up with
black wall street
you know tulsa all these places and
you know it wasn't racism that that
caused
the massacres and riots that followed
you know
it was basically an intolerable
um collective sharing economy
a different economic system emerging
that was absolutely unacceptable
to the juggernaut of the that free
market economy that was
well not that it's a free market with
the monopolistic economy that was being
created
you know so you had um you had
adjacent white communities that were
far more wealthy but far less prosperous
than the poor black neighborhoods coming
out so they had to be destroyed
you know so i guess i don't know you'll
find the answer in there
yeah i'm just it's really striking you
know as you're talking i'm thinking that
this is
this is one of the perhaps key arguments
of the
i don't know quite what to describe it
because as you mentioned giving it a
name but let's say
what i've called it kind of wokism or
like the kind of
the now the genesis of
post-structuralism which is that
certain ways of knowing um basically
oppress other ways of knowing which i
think there's a lot of validity to that
you know what you're just describing
what happened in tulsa for example of
like a different way emerging and then
the dominant culture
what i think renee isa called the
dominator society kind of coming in and
suppressing it you know that is i think
a valid
aspect of it but then there's always
that balancing point it seems between
also honoring the perspective of say
rationality and finding some
way to blend them together i mean do you
think that's doable
is that like what what is what's your
synthesis
what is what is it that's indicating to
you that that rationality is no longer
the dominant worldview
i think it is i think it it it is still
the dominant world view
yeah you know we don't need to
like you know um silence all these
people who are going too far
to try and make some room for the
dominant
ideology on the planet it's everywhere
it's the structure of everything from
uber to
anything else you know it's already
there
like relax it's it's it's it hasn't gone
anywhere it's still the dominant way of
thinking
on the planet and you have to conform to
it
and you know you can complain to the
chinese as much as you like but they
still have to learn english
in order to do business in this world
and they still have to go by
the the the calendar of the anglo-sphere
everybody's got to go with the same
calendar that starts with jesus's
birthday
um you know
you know yeah everybody still has to
exist in the same institutions that are
based on that uh
you know that sort of positivist
framework you know
and there are there are some things that
have made some room
uh to to try and you know see a few
different points of view
and to use a few other tools that will
actually help
um you know like i said before even with
your genetics research and everything
else
but uh yeah i mean i think people look
at
sort of the volume of the minority that
are you know
um screaming workisms and
and they kind of equate that the quality
of the volume to the the quantity of you
know how far it's spread
it's certainly not the dominant ideology
on the planet
although you know a lot of people just
i mean it is the thing you know um
you know amazon might put up a black
lives matter sticker and make a
statement
um but it's not changing their
operations
they don't have to change anything
structurally all they have to do is say
the thing
and so everybody goes oh look they're
you know they're taking over or whatever
it's nothing's changed the structure's
still there
the prison industrial complex is still a
thing
yeah you know i yeah that's not going
that's not going anywhere and that
requires
inequality so post-modernism uh critical
race theory all these things
they're really just trying to bring an
awareness of power
to the table because power is a variable
in all of these things that you want to
study and if you ignore that variable
a really key variable then your findings
are invalid
your data is invalid your analysis is
invalid you do need to
at least like you need to factor in
power as a variable
because it just is it exists and it's
great that your opinion might be the
power doesn't exist
like oh what are all these people
complaining about
um you know that's great if that's your
opinion
but that's not rational
if you're claiming a rational viewpoint
and you're ignoring power
that that's not rational brass
yeah yeah and i i think for me
that the critique and the understanding
the way power moves and the way it works
and the way it plays out in society
is the most valuable aspect of
post-modernism and is why i think
foucault is so important
at the same time i would love to get you
boring though
yeah yeah but yeah that's how i use
foucault to help me fall asleep at night
it's so dense i get two pages yeah that
kind of french
philosophy in general or kind of french
critical theory is
yeah is hard it's quite dense
um but so i just wanted to kind of look
at one example in particular like so i
i'm with you on the uh on the fact that
we have to look at power
and we have to consider that but again
where does it start to become its own
power game is my question right so for
example there was this um
there was this i don't know if you saw
it a big spat on twitter about the idea
the statement two plus two equals five
and it it was made as a sort of pithy
remark by
i think james lindsay who's a very
contentious character and i
also question his um approach and
world view in various ways but he posted
that and then other people took it up as
like yeah two plus two equals four
is is basically white supremacy because
it's one kind of rational way of knowing
coming in and determining everything
else and then other people were arguing
yeah well hang on like it's also
somewhat a universal through cultures
and other people said no it's not
what would be your take on it because
some people would look at that and go
yeah it's important to be aware of power
but even with maths
is that valid what do you write here's
the thing
indigenous knowledge it's a lot of
people think it's it's
static and and just remains the same for
thousands of years
but it doesn't um we're always taking on
new knowledge but we do it rigorously
you know things are tested very
rigorously before they're incorporated
and basically the the inquiry
the method of inquiry that we have is
about drilling down to the foundational
story
of that new of the thing that we're
looking at
so you know base as soon as you're
saying that i'm thinking through
trying to get down to what's the
foundational story here um
and it's seldom what people are talking
about
you know people are seldom
seldom angry for the reason they think
and they are never
angry for the reason they say so
you know you drill down to the story and
there's lots of stories there
but the foundational story on that
silly little debate because it is silly
it's it's obviously
you know it's like you might call it a
bad faith conversation
you know um but i i guess you know the
foundational story is
where did those uh numerals come from in
the first place you know no one's saying
like you know
i i plus i i equals iv are they
they're going one plus one where did
they come from
they're they're arabic numerals
and and that's that uh that's the the
project of westernism is to just go
around the world and plunder
all kinds of stuff and to remove it from
its context and build
you know this uh canon of knowledge
that'll be the center of all things
um so i i would say that's the
foundational
that's part of the foundational story
there so you'd start you
i'd probably want to ask an arab
mathematician what he thinks about that
you know because they have lots of
i don't know they have lots of ideas
about you know five who's unlucky and
all that sort of thing
so they probably wouldn't want two plus
two to equal five i don't know
that's just that would be a a fun little
experiment
um look i recommend it to my
university like the they have a a
diversity kind of you know um
every university has this they have a
diversity program where they do all
kinds of things
and i went look it's lovely that you've
got like a poster of a girl and a hijab
there
um that's nice but that's not diversity
and inclusion diversity inclusion would
be like
you know if you were targeting that
segment if you really wanted to
like equally value that culture's
knowledge then you'd say right
every research project with more than a
million dollars funding
um um has to allow this team of
of of arab scientists to have a second
run at their data
you know so once you've analyzed your
data and you've got your findings
you then have to submit it to this um
arab speaking committee
who in arabic speaking their own
language will go through and analyze
analyze your data and see if they come
up with the same findings
and that will be a test for rigor i mean
if you really did value that culture and
their knowledge
and their um facility with these
numerals
which has a far longer tradition than
yours
then give them another go of your data
and see if they can replicate your
results
if they can't have another look at it
bros um
they didn't like that idea that would be
actual diversity
and that would be productive diversity
they don't they just want the pretty
girl in the hijab on the poster
you know um they might they might put
her on the
on the board of something or they might
make her a vice chancellor or something
like that and everyone will feel good
for about five minutes but you know
you can't people trying to rescue this
system
but then you've got the sjws on the
other side they're trying to change the
system they think that they can make
this civilization
fair you you can't so as i said before
it's like trying to make your dog into a
vegan um
he's one or two things that's gonna
happen he's gonna die or he's gonna eat
you
you know this this civilization this
system
this economic system you know it's a dog
and you don't want to be a vegan
can't be vegan so so would your
suggestion be that we let the dog die
and that we see what happens after that
or or you know we're in the situation
whether we like it or not
whoever we are wherever we are so you
know
um i don't think there's there's there
aren't any solutions and
and i don't know anybody who thinks
they've got a solution or they have a
plan or a design
or anything like that um they're an
idiot
you you can't dynamic systems don't
operate like that
you know you have a thing called
emergence we know this we know the
science on it
and you know emergence is the only thing
that can deal with
these kind of complexities so all you
can do is foster the conditions for
emergence
you know if i was going to go straight
from my own like psychotic ideology i
would just be like yeah shoot the dog
just shoot it shoot it
get a goat if you wanted to eat veggies
jesus um that's
that's where i'd go to but you know that
would just be narcissism my narcissism
talking
i don't i can't have a solution nobody
can
you know that's that's insane there
would just be another stupid complicated
tinkered bloody teetering horrible
corruptable system that would come out
from that
yeah um i think we're just gonna have to
go through
all this and you know if you're
unfortunate enough to have
stepped into the twitter sphere and
started wrestling the pigs
then um then well i'm sorry but you're
you're you've done wrestle the pig and
and now you're covered in the same muck
yeah
and and that's just and then that's just
something you're just gonna have to go
through
um yeah see what you pick up when you're
in there
yeah how do you feel it's
it's so interesting what you're saying
comes right back to something we're
talking about before which
you know this narcissism this idea that
we can control
that this idea that the world is there
for us to control rather than
you know a lot of um cultures a lot of
kind of
cultures from ancient you know
pre-socratic
you know in the west as well as around
the world had a sense that
we we need to look after the sacred you
know we are stewards of the sacred
sacred isn't just there to look after us
we look after it and then there's this
similar i can think
kind of attitude towards the world it's
like kind of what can this system give
me
me me me as opposed to surrendering and
allowing it to emerge
that is so opposite to what western
culture is set up to do
and the value systems that that
we live by you know so i'm just i'm just
curious about
what are some of the the axioms as a
terrible word for it but what are some
of the values that that aboriginal
culture
would use to go hey chill out
you know and and be in that flow rather
than trying to control it
um the terrible answer to that is that
there are none
because they're not needed
like um you know so so
aboriginal culture at its foundation
it never separated society from nature
so
it didn't have to separate all those
abstracts and name those things and then
come up with rules
uh to put that the law is natural law
and the law
is in the land um and it's it's
all around you and you have to follow
that
um and and those laws are inalienable
you can't
change it like a bill of rights or a
charter or
you know a um which is in america always
talking about that
what's that document the founding
fathers
i don't know why i can't remember it now
it starts with c constitution that's
right
we apparently there's one for australia
too but i mean that's just
a funny little temporary tweakable thing
you know it'll disappear along with the
paper it's written on
um but you know there is permanent
inalienable law
and it is in the land it's in it's in
your dna
you know it's it's in every natural
impulse that
you have and
and i guess the the um
the pathological impulses that people
have
you know in response to a really sick
environment a sick
habitat and a sick system that's not
them
you know a lot of people think that's
our nature is that you know
we just run around we're just raping
like that's what if where
we remove this rule of law or anything
else it's just it's just rape and murder
until we're all dead
um but uh that's not what happened for
the last million years
and it's been a million years of um
symbolic reasoning
and meaning making at least
because that's the oldest example of
symbolic reasoning found with the
the carved shells the beautiful carved
shells from the
homo erectus in asia
you know homo erectus was making meaning
and that's that's a million years old
at least who knows how far back before
that you know we do have a lot of
thought
and a lot of um you know ways of being
behind us and this last five minutes is
a blip
and the ways we're behaving now these
knee-jerk responses and
programmed responses these aren't our
natures
it's it's not what's natural rebel
wisdom was set up to make
sense of the world at a deeper level
than the mainstream media
it was built for these times of crisis
and change
which is why we want to do what we can
to meet the challenge of the times
more films and also for our rebel wisdom
members
weekly sense making calls with our
amazing interviewees
and also we're introducing the wisdom
gym
a place to practice some of the skills
that we've talked about on the channel
thanks for watching and see you soon